<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BATS</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Bulletin of Applied Transgender Studies</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>BATS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2769-2124</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Northwestern University Libraries</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Evanson (IL)</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Copyright 2023 The Authors</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2023</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/legalcode">
<license-p>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0
International (CC BY-NC-ND 4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>weight: title: ’’ subtitle: ’’ article: type: research-article #
book-review, brief-report, research-article doi: ’’ heading: ’’ #
Original Article, Brief Report, Book Review volume: ’’ issue: ’’ fpage:
lpage: filename: ’’ author: - orcid: surname: ’’ given_name: ’’ name: ’’
# First Name Last Name email: ’’ affiliation: organization: ’’
department: ’’ isni: ’’ ror: ’’ # info available at https://ror.org/
bio: |</p>
<p>_date: day: ’’ month: ’’ year: ’’ abstract: |</p>
<p>tags: - references: |</p>
<p>nocite: “[@*]” references: - author: - family: Association given:
American Psychiatric id: apa2013diagnostic issued: 2013 publisher:
American Psychiatric Association title: “Diagnostic and statistical
manual of mental disorders: DSM-5” title-short: Diagnostic and
statistical manual of mental disorders type: book url:
“https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596” - author: - family:
Association given: American Psychiatric id: apa2022diagnostic issued:
2022 publisher: American Psychiatric Association Publishing title:
Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, fifth edition,
text revision (DSM-5-TR) type: book url:
“https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425787” - author: - family:
Anderson given: J. - family: Holland given: E. container-title:
“Sensoria: A Journal of Mind, Brain &amp; Culture” id:
anderson2015legacy issue: 1 issued: 2015 page: 4-15 title: “The legacy
of medicalising ‘homosexuality’: A discussion on the historical effects
of non-heterosexual diagnostic classifications” title-short: “The legacy
of medicalising ‘homosexuality’” type: article-journal url:
“https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=a9h&amp;AN=102039100&amp;site=ehost-live”
volume: 11</p>
<p>Coltan J. Schoenike</p>
<p>is a PhD student and Teaching Fellow in the Department of Applied
Psychology at Antioch University New England.</p>
<p>cschoenike@antioch.edu</p>
<p><italic>Abstract:</italic> Deeply-seeded issues of cisgenderism and
discriminatory bias are continuing problems that slow equal rights
advances and facilitate further harm for transgender and gender diverse
communities - and research literature is no exception. A salient example
of this is the historical and ongoing works of Dr. Kenneth Zucker and
his colleagues. Previous research by Ansara and Hegarty (2012) has
already illustrated this in detail, noting these researchers were often
the most cisgenderist while having the highest degrees of influence.
This review of literature examines a collection of Zucker’s first,
second, and third author works from 2010-2022 using Anasara and
Hegarty’s (2012) framework of binarism, misgendering, and pathologizing
to assess cisgenderism within the writing. A lot occurred over those
twelve years, including Zucker’s work as chair of the <italic>Diagnostic
and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> work group for the
gender dysphoria diagnosis, the controversial closure of his youth
gender clinic in Toronto, and massive increases in visibility and
discussion of transgender healthcare. In many ways, it appears that
Zucker’s pattern of cisgenderism has continued. This review of
literature explores this pattern in detail and offers insights as to why
many of these ideologies are harmful to transgender and gender diverse
communities.</p>
<p><italic>Keywords:</italic> transgender; cisgenderism; gender
identity; Zucker; research literature</p>
<p>Research has the power to influence policy and thus lives, and so the
duty for care in the research (and research<italic>ers</italic>) we
publish and platform is instrumental in the potential to facilitate
great progress or terrible harm. A clear example of the latter would be
the body of work by Dr. Kenneth J. Zucker and other members of his
“Invisible College,” a connected system of authors in collaboration with
each other. Zucker and his invisible college were prominently identified
a decade ago as some of the most discriminatory, yet most frequently
published and cited research surrounding gender identity (Ansara &amp;
Hegarty 2012). In the years since this finding, the harm of Zucker’s
work has only become clearer with the closure of his gender identity
clinic for youth where he was accused by some clients of engaging in
conversion practices (Ashley 2022a 3–9). While issues around the
investigation led to apologies from Zucker’s former employers and a
settlement in his favor, it is nonetheless important to note that the
clinic remained closed and concerns around Zucker’s practices -
conversion or not - remained (The Canadian Press 2018).</p>
<p> Despite the constantly accumulating evidence of harm, the power
Zucker holds in influencing research and healthcare for trans and
gender-nonconforming communities remains, including as the chair of the
American Psychiatric Association (APA)’s work group that handles
diagnoses related to gender identity in the most recent version of the
<italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic>
(<italic>DSM</italic>), the fifth edition text revision
(<italic>DSM-5-TR</italic>) which was only released last year (American
Psychiatric Association 2022 xviii). Yes, a researcher with years of
documented accusations of cisgenderist bias and self-admission of
approaches that could be considered conversion practices (Zucker,
Bradley, et al. 2012) is at the helm of the work group that establishes
the definitions of transgender and gender diverse experiences.</p>
<p>To illustrate this problem further, this article reviews published
articles since 2010 where Kenneth J. Zucker was listed as first, second,
or third author and was related to gender identity. The year 2010 was
specifically selected as a starting point with the intention of covering
at least one decade of published material, especially in order to
explore the prevalence of cisgenderist ideology even after public and
published critiques such as Ansara and Hegarty’s (2012; 2014). This time
range also allowed for inclusions of early discussions that were
informing the soon-to-be-released <italic>DSM-5</italic>, of which
Zucker would chair the work group discussing gender dysphoria as a
mental health diagnosis (American Psychiatric Association 2013; Zucker
2010; Zucker et al. 2013).</p>
<p>Throughout the articles reviewed, concepts and approaches are
critiqued and the various ways cisgenderist ideology appears is
explained. Informing my own critiques will be the previous literature on
this issue as well as other literature noting the severity of this kind
of harm and what a proposed alternative could include. Most importantly,
much of the supporting literature is often informed by researchers of
diverse gender identities and theories that value autonomy and the
rights of marginalized communities to speak as the experts of their own
experiences. As a point of researcher reflexivity, I too am a researcher
and practitioner within the trans and gender diverse communities and the
communities Zucker and others often discuss. Critical analysis of where
our stories come from is an ethical responsibility, and we owe it to
communities that we work with to reflect on whether they’ve been given
the chance to tell their own stories themself (Iantaffi 2020).</p>
<sec id="establishing-basis-for-critique">
  <title>Establishing Basis for Critique</title>
  <sec id="understanding-cisgenderism">
    <title>Understanding cisgenderism</title>
    <p>To further understand the concerns illustrated throughout this
    review, it is important to outline the “what”s and “why”s of the
    critique</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
